Finding Aid for the William Mckendree Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
William Mckendree Papers
2016
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0277
.84 linear feet
Biography of William McKendree
William McKendree was born in Virginia in 1757. In 1810 his family moved to Sumner County, Tennessee. At the start of the American Revolution, McKendree joined a group of Tennessee volunteers. After leaving the army he served as a school teacher for a bit. He joined the Methodist Episcopal Church in 1787 and worked as a minister. He worked in places such as Virginia, Maryland, North Carolina, and South Carolina. In 1801, he was sent to oversee the church of Ohio, Kentucky, Tennessee, and Virginia. After a number of years ministering to those areas he was appointed to become a bishop. William McKendree was the first Methodist Bishop born in the United States. A school in Lebanon, Illinois is named after him because of the missionary work he did there. He died in 1835 in Sumner County, Tennessee at his brother’s house.
Scope and Content Note
The William McKendree Papers are comprised of .83 linear feet of correspondence, sermons and collected materials of Bishop McKendree. Also contained within these papers is his personal diary as well as a church business journal and several of William McKendree’s sermons. Aside from McKendree’s related papers there are a few Methodist relics such as a classbook of the year 1796, a partial diary of Hester Ann Rogers and outlines of sermons by Samuel Bradburn. Of note is a letter from John Wesley and a square of bedclothes from the bed in which John Wesley died.
Included in the collection are three small rolls of microfilm that were held by the Divinity Library until 2015 when they were transferred to Special Collections. These rolls contain reproductions of some of the papers.
- Outgoing Correspondence, May 11, 1811 - Oct. 26, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Outgoing Correspondence, Feb. 26, 1821 - Dec. 8, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Outgoing Correspondence, July 21, 1825 - April 17, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Outgoing Correspondence, March 10, 1828 - Feb. 8, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Outgoing Correspondence, – Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Incoming Correspondence, June 3, 1793 - March 3, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Incoming Correspondence, Dec. 12, 1809 – Feb. 2, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Incoming Correspondence, Feb. 15, 1810 – March 20, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Incoming Correspondence, April 21, 1811 – March 9, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Incoming Correspondence, May 24, 1819 – Oct. 23, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Incoming Correspondence, Jan. 23, 1822 –July 24, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Incoming Correspondence, Aug. 1822 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Incoming Correspondence, Sept. 5, 1822 – Dec. 28, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Incoming Correspondence, April 29, 1823 – June 30, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Incoming Correspondence, July 19, 1823 – Aug. 25, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Incoming Correspondence, Aug. 27, 1823 – Sept. 18, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Incoming Correspondence, Oct. 9, 1823 – Feb. 23, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Incoming Correspondence, March 17, 1824 – June 30, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Incoming Correspondence, July 17, 1824 – Aug. 31, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Incoming Correspondence, Nov. 1, 1824 – Dec. 14, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Incoming Correspondence, Aug. 6, 1825 – April 20, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Incoming Correspondence, May 3, 1826 – March 31, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Incoming Correspondence, March 30, 1829 – May 21, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Incoming Correspondence, Jan. 14, 1830 - March 31, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Incoming Correspondence, Dec. 1832- October 15, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Incoming Correspondence, Nov. 22, 1833 – Oct. 22, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Undated Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Unidentified Correspondence Classbook, dated1796 belonging to W. Rogers showing income and expenditures of Methodist Conference. Partial diary of Hester Ann Rogers. Three outlines of sermons by Samuel Bradburn. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Relics of John Wesley – Letter and bedclothes (scrap) of John Wesley (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Relics of John Wesley – Letter and bedclothes (scrap) of John Wesley (Box 2, Folder 29)
- William McKendree’s Diary – May 7, 1790 – Feb. 18, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- William McKendree’s Journal of Church Business – 1810-1814 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Book Listing Methodist Episcopal ministers (Box 2, Folder 3)
- William McKendree’s Sermons Improvement - title of two; Angelic Annunciation of Christ’s Birth - Based on John 3:16, 17, Preached at Nashville Camp Ground, Aug. 3, 1834. Based on Isaiah 45:22. Based on Philippians 1:21. Book of Sermons: Christian Perfection On the Possibility of Falling from Grace Absolute Predestination Extracts from Mr. Clelland’s Dialogue Extracts from Mr. R. Mach’s Refutation of the Chain of Lorenzo The Progress of Methodism (Box 2, Folder 4)
- John Fletcher’s Sermons (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Plan of the Circuits –chart (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Newspaper Clippings, “The Life of Pioneer in Methodism.” Methodist Review, “A Critical Descriptive catalogue of All the Editions of the Discipline of the Methodist Church in America from 1785-1808.” (Box 2, Folder 7)